Guide to the Arthur Liman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur L. Liman papers
1950-2001
MS 1762
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18.75
The papers consist of correspondence, diaries, legal documents, speeches, writings, printed material, photographs, and audiovisual materials that document the career of Arthur Liman. The papers emphasize the 1987 Iran-Contra hearings but also document many of Liman's other professional activities, including the Attica Prison uprising investigation and the Michael Milken trial. The papers contain an extensive collection of audiotapes and videotapes featuring conversations with and interviews of Liman.
Liman, Arthur L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ellen Liman, 1999, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiotapes and videotapes, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Consult the finding aid and/or a reference archivist to determine availability of a use copy or the process required to generate a use copy.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: Series I. Legal Papers, 1963-1995. Series II. Personal Papers and Photographs, 1950-1999. Series III. Writings, 1957-1998. Series IV. Audiovisual Materials, 1978-1998.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the career of Arthur Liman, primarily the period from the Iran-Contra investigation in 1987 until his death in 1997. The Iran-Contra diary and audiotapes are of particular interest as they provide insight into Liman's private thoughts during the hearings. A movie script Liman later wrote about Iran-Contra reflects his opinion about how the events took place. The collection offers a wide variety of visual resources, including photographs of Liman from the early 1950s through the 1990s. Videotapes in the collection include copies of many of Liman's television interviews concerning Iran-Contra. The correspondence in the collection offers little personal perspective and the papers include limited documentation of Liman's private practice or his law firm.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Liman was born on November 5, 1932, in New York City. He graduated from Harvard in 1954 with a B.A. degree and proceeded to Yale Law School, graduating first in his class in 1957. Over the next forty years, Liman worked in disparate arenas to build a distinguished legal career, combining numerous public assignments and a private practice that included representing some of the country's most prosperous individuals and corporations.
After leaving Yale Law School in 1957, Liman joined the firm of Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison in New York City. In 1961, he left the firm to become an assistant United States attorney under Robert M. Morgenthau and developed expertise in business law. Liman continued in the field of business law upon his return to Paul, Weiss in 1963, specializing in cases involving securities fraud and other white-collar crimes. According to newspaper accounts and tributes from his friends and colleagues, Liman was known for his thorough preparation and extraordinary commitment to his clients and was considered one of the best trial lawyers of his time. As a result, he attracted many powerful and well-known clients. Not shy of controversy, Liman represented junk bond merchant Michael Milken and corporate raider Carl Icahn. Adroit in corporate backrooms, he facilitated the merger of Time Inc. and Warner Communications.
Despite his success in private practice, Liman gained more notoriety as a result of his public assignments. Two appointments in particular defined his career. In 1972, he served as chief counsel of the New York State Special Commission on the Attica Prison uprising. The commission was charged with investigating the uprising at Attica State Prison in 1971 in which forty-three inmates and guards died. The commission's final report, which blamed prison conditions and state officials for the violence, was published in book form and nominated for a National Book Award. Liman's most widely-known assignment came in 1987 when he was appointed chief counsel to the Senate Select Committee on Secret Military Assistance to Iran and the Nicaraguan Opposition (the Iran-Contra Committee). The committee held hearings to make public the details of the clandestine operation selling weapons to Iran in exchange for the release of hostages and directing the arms proceeds to rebels in Nicaragua. The hearings, especially his cross-examination of Colonel Oliver North, put Liman in the national spotlight. The attention was not easy to bear, however, as the committee received criticism both for being too hard and too soft on witnesses and for its inability to trace knowledge of the operation to President Ronald Reagan.
Liman's public service extended beyond Attica and Iran-Contra. Among his other assignments were a 1979 suit in which he represented New York City against subway car manufacturers, winning a $72 million award, and heading the 1985 investigation of the New York City medical examiner amid charges that the examiner had provided false autopsy reports. In addition, he was active in organizations working to provide legal representation to those who could not afford it otherwise, serving terms as president of the Legal Aid Society and chairman of the Legal Action Center.
Arthur Liman married Ellen Fogelson, a writer, painter, and interior decorator, in 1959. They had three children: Lewis, Emily, and Douglas.
Arthur Liman died on July 17, 1997, in New York City.
Iran-Contra Affair, 1985-1990; Liman, Arthur L.; Liman, Ellen, 1936-; Milken, Michael; Attica Prison
- Legal Papers, 1963-1995, undated; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains notes, correspondence, photocopies of legal documents, printed materials, photographs, and press clippings relating to Arthur Liman's legal career. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject or case name. The series includes material from both of Liman's best-known public service assignments, the committees to investigate the Attica State Prison uprising in 1972 and the Iran-Contra affair in 1987. Of particular interest are the diaries Liman kept on both occasions. In keeping with the original order of the collection, correspondence regarding specific cases resides in this series, although the bulk of the correspondence in this collection is in Series II. The scrapbooks in Series II contain more newspaper clippings regarding Attica State Prison and Iran-Contra. Series IV includes audiovisual material on Iran-Contra and Michael Milken.
  - ALI-ABA [American Legal Institute - American Bar Association] course materials, 1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Attica State Prison uprising
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
    - Correspondence, 1972, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      General
      See: Oversize Folder 1
    - Diary, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Official report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Official statements, 1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, [1971-1972], undated (Box 1, Folder 9 - 10)
      See: Oversize Folder 2
  - Bar admission applications, 1959, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chase v. Turner & Newell
    - Hearing, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Trial notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 13 - 29)
    - Negatives and slides, [1971-1972], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Christie's
    - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Opening remarks, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31 - 32)
  - Commission on the Administration of Justice [Recommendations to the Governor Regarding the Administration of the Criminal Justice System], 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - GAF [USA v. GAF Corporation court brief], 1990 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Gulf Coast Leaseholders case
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Darby testimony, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Opening statement, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Stenographer's minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Iran-Contra
    - Clippings, 1987-1988, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Closing statement, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Committee documents, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1989, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Court document - U.S. v. North, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Diary, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Ellen Liman's diary, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Ellen Liman's sketches of hearings, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Ephemera [business cards, badges, calendar, etc.], 1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Establishment of the Iran-Contra Senate Select Committee, 1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Hearing notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Hearing transcripts, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Photographs, [1987], undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - President's notes [Ronald Reagan], 1987, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Report of the Select Committee on Intelligence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Witness lists and hearing schedules, 1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Judiciary committee application, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Legal Action Center, 1995-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1984-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 57 - 58)
  - Milken, Michael
    - Arraignment, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 59 - 60)
    - Case chronology, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Clippings, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Fatico hearing findings, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Indictment, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Memoranda, 1990, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Memorandum in support of a reduction of sentence, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Sentencing transcript, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Settlement, 1990, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Warehouse index of Milken documents, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - New York City Medical Examiner investigation
    - Clippings, 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Report on the New York City Medical Examiner, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 72 - 78)
  - NYC/MTA R-46 [The City of New York and the New York City Transit Authority v. Pullman Incorporated, et al]
    - Clippings, 1980-1988 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Trial transcript, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison, 1965-1997, undated (Box 5, Folder 81 - 87)
- Personal Papers and Photographs, 1950-1999, undated; Series II
  The series includes correspondence, printed material, photographs, and press clippings arranged alphabetically. Routine correspondence from Arthur Liman's friends and colleagues, not specifically relating to a legal case, comprises a significant part of the series and is arranged chronologically. Letters of condolence received by Liman's family after his death in 1997 are arranged alphabetically according to the sender's last name. The series also includes biographical information and Liman's notes and papers from college and law school. The series concludes with scrapbooks, which consist largely of newspaper clippings and document Liman's time at Harvard and Yale and his work as chief counsel for the Attica and Iran-Contra committees.
  - Biographical information, 1963, 1988-1997 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1971-1997, undated (Box 6, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Liman, Arthur
      - 1956-1987 (Box 6, Folder 4 - 11)
      - 1988-1997, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 12 - 20)
    - Liman, Ellen, 1960-1998, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Letters of condolence, 1997
      - A-M (Box 8, Folder 22 - 27)
      - N-Z (Box 9, Folder 28 - 31)
  - Events featuring Arthur Liman, 1973-1991, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Financial papers, 1961, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Genealogy [includes copies of census records, 1899-1920], undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Honors and awards, 1978-1999, undated (Box 9, Folder 35 - 36)
  - Interview transcripts, 1995, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Memorial service, tributes, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 38 - 40)
  - Photographs
    - Clients, 1979, 1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Family, undated (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Judicial conference, Circa 1970s
      See: Oversize Folder 3
    - Miscellaneous [various photographs of Arthur Liman], 1987-1994, undated (Box 10, Folder 43 - 49)
  - School papers
    - 1950-1953, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 50 - 52)
    - 1952-1957, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 53 - 61)
    - 1954-1957, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 62 - 65)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1951-1977, n.d. [includes photographs and correspondence from Liman's time at Harvard and Yale, newspaper clippings about the Attica Prison uprising] (Box 13, Folder 66 - 69)
    - 1971-1979, n.d. [includes newspaper clippings about the investigation of Attica, honors received by Liman] (Box 14, Folder 70 - 72)
    - 1987-1988, n.d. [includes newspaper clippings about Iran-Contra] (Box 15, Folder 73 - 75)
- Writings, 1957-1998, undated; Series III
  The series contains transcripts of Arthur Liman's speeches, copies of his written work, and select correspondence regarding his autobiography. It is arranged alphabetically by sections. The majority of the series consists of drafts of Liman's autobiography, Lawyer: A Life of Counsel and Controversy, published in 1998. Most of the correspondence is between Ellen Liman and Peter Israel, who served as an assistant on the autobiography. The series also includes a movie script and outline Liman wrote about Iran-Contra. Audio and videocassette recordings of some of Liman's speeches are included in Series IV.
  - Articles, 1957-1996, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Lawyer: A Life of Counsel and Controversy [autobiography]
    - Correspondence, 1997-1998, undated (Box 16, Folder 2 - 4)
    - Drafts, 1996-1997, undated (Box 21, Box 22, Box 19, Box 20, Box 25, Box 26, Box 23, Box 24, Box 29, Box 27, Box 28, Box 33, Box 17, Folder 5 - 128, Box 34, Box 18, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32)
    - Outlines, undated (Box 35, Folder 129)
    - Publicity, 1998, undated (Box 35, Folder 130)
    - Research, 1957-1985, undated (Box 35, Folder 131 - 137)
    - Research, 1957-1985, undated (Box 36, Folder 138)
  - Memoranda, 1995-1997, undated (Box 36, Folder 139)
  - Movie script and outline, undated (Box 36, Folder 140)
  - Speeches, 1972, 1980-1996, undated (Box 37, Folder 141 - 150)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1978-1998, undated; Series IV
  The series includes audiotapes in cassette and microcassette format and videotapes in VHS and U-matic format. The series is arranged by format and chronologically within each format. The tapes in boxes 41, 42, and 43 are largely recordings of private conversations during Arthur Liman's Iran-Contra assignment and are the audiocassette tapes with the greatest research value. The tape in box 43 is the audio version of Liman's Iran-Contra diary, the transcript of which is in Series I. The majority of the microcassette tapes were recorded during the Iran-Contra hearings. The microcassette recordings capture Liman at his most candid regarding the Iran-Contra hearings and the Michael Milken sentence. The VHS videotapes in boxes 70, 72, 89, and 91 contain the most in-depth interviews of Liman.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiotapes and videotapes, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Consult the finding aid and/or a reference archivist to determine availability of a use copy or the process required to generate a use copy.
  - Audiocassette tapes of Arthur Liman
    - Speech at Legal Aid dinner in honor of Simon Rifkind [original; fifteen minutes; restricted]., 1984 April 10 (Box 38)
    - Commencement speech at the Fieldston School graduation ceremony [original; fifteen minutes; restricted]., 1984 (Box 39)
    - "Morning Edition" (National Public Radio) story on the Iran-Contra chief counsels [original; ten minutes; restricted]., 1987 May 18 (Box 40)
    - Dictating thoughts while preparing for the Iran-Contra hearings; topics include gaining government clearance and hiring a legal staff [original; ninety minutes; restricted]., [1987] (Box 41)
    - Conversations between Arthur Liman, Ellen Liman, and Mark Belnick during preparation for the Iran-Contra hearings [original; seventy-five minutes; restricted]., [1987] (Box 42)
    - Dictating journal entries during the Iran-Contra hearings [original; ninety minutes; restricted]., [1987] (Box 43)
    - Radio Yale interview re: Iran-Contra hearings [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., 1987 (Box 44)
    - Speech at Yale Law School re: Iran-Contra hearings [original; ninety minutes; restricted]., 1987 October 16 (Box 45)
    - Speech at Harvard Hall re: Iran-Contra hearings [original; ninety minutes; restricted]., 1987 November 30 (Box 46)
    - "Free Speech and the First Amendment" panel discussion at Harvard reunion [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1989 (Box 47)
    - Interviewed by Mark Belnick [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1996 December 13 (Box 48)
    - Paul, Weiss Litigation Department lunch honoring Arthur Liman [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1997 August 6 (Box 49)
    - Answering questions about Iran-Contra [original; sixty minutes; restricted; poor sound quality]., undated (Box 50)
    - Answering questions about Iran-Contra [original; twenty minutes; restricted; poor sound quality]., undated (Box 51)
  - Audio microcassette tapes of Arthur Liman
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Phone and general conversations re: Iran-Contra [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., [1987] May (Box 52)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Phone conversations and dictation re: Iran-Contra [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., [1987] May (Box 53)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Phone conversations and dictation re: Iran-Contra [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., [1987] June (Box 54)
    - Phone conversations re: Iran-Contra [original; thirty minutes; restricted; poor sound quality]., [1987] June (Box 55)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Phone conversations and dictation re: Iran-Contra [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] June-July (Box 56)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Phone conversations re: Iran-Contra [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] July (Box 57)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Conversations re: Iran-Contra [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] August (Box 58)
    - [Arthur and Ellen Liman] Conversations re: Iran-Contra [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] August (Box 59)
    - Radio Yale interview and general conversations [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] Aug, October (Box 60)
    - Speeches and a staff meeting re: Iran-Contra. [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] November (Box 61)
    - Speeches re: Iran-Contra [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., [1987] November-December (Box 62)
    - Speeches at New York Public Library and Park Avenue Synagogue [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., 1988 January 21, February 2 (Box 63)
    - [Michael Milken?]. Dictation re: the Milken case [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., [1990] (Box 64)
    - Phone conversations re: the Milken sentence [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., [1990] (Box 65)
    - Phone conversations re: the Milken sentence [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., [1990] (Box 66)
    - [Michael Milken?]. Dictation re: stock news [original; forty minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 67)
    - Dictation re: the Milken case [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 68)
  - VHS videotapes of Arthur Liman
    - 50thbirthday party [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1982 (Box 69)
    - "Reminiscences: Partner Interviews," interview by Ernest Rubenstein [original; one hundred minutes; restricted]., 1986 (Box 70)
    - Discussion of trial strategy with staff [original; ninety minutes; restricted; poor sound quality]., 1986 (Box 71)
    - BBC TV, interview by Tim Sebastian [original; seventy minutes; restricted]., 1987 December (Box 72)
    - C-SPAN interview [original; thirty-five minutes; restricted]., 1987 December 17 (Box 73)
    - Iran-Contra hearings, Liman questioning Albert Hakim [original; 180 minutes; restricted]., 1987 (Box 74)
    - "Good Morning America" interview; tape also includes clips from other interviews re: Iran-Contra and George Bush, Oliver North, Robert McFarlane, Ronald Reagan, and Lawrence Walsh [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., 1988 January 21, undated (Box 75)
    - Speech at the University of Virginia re: Iran-Contra, University of Virginia [original; sixty minutes; restricted; poor sound quality]., 1988 March 22 (Box 76)
    - "CBS News Nightwatch" interview [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., 1988 March 24 (Box 77)
    - Speech re: Iran-Contra [original; seventy minutes; restricted]., 1988 April 8 (Box 78)
    - BBC TV interview [original; fifteen minutes; restricted]., 1989January 5 (Box 79)
    - "Nightline" re: Oliver North jury selection [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., 1989 February 1 (Box 80)
    - "Lin Broadcasting vs. Metromedia," arguing a case before the New York State Court of Appeals [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1989 May 31 (Box 81)
    - "60 Minutes" segment on Felix Rodriguez (Iran-Contra) [original; twenty minutes; Liman appears for roughly one minute; restricted]., 1989 October 22 (Box 82)
    - "The Legal Aid Society," public relations video for the Legal Aid Society [original; twenty minutes; Liman appears for roughly one minute; restricted]., 1989December (Box 83)
    - "Ethics in America: #5 Anatomy of a Corporate Takeover," Liman part of a hypothetical case study [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1989 (Box 84)
    - Servant of Justice award ceremony [original; sixty minutes; restricted; poor sound and picture quality], 1991 April (Box 85)
    - 60thbirthday party [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1992 (Box 86)
    - "Celebration of a Life: Steven J. Ross" [original; thirty minutes; Liman appears for roughly thirty seconds; restricted]., 1993 March 30 (Box 87)
    - Senate Committee testimony, Liman argues in favor of renewing the Independent Counsel Act [original; 120 minutes; restricted]., 1993 (Box 88)
      Recording on tape ends abruptly.
    - "Charlie Rose" interview [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., 1995 June 16 (Box 89)
    - "In Memory of Judge Simon H. Rifkind" [original; ninety minutes; restricted; Liman speaks for fifteen minutes]., 1995 November 29 (Box 90)
    - "Reminiscences: Partner Interviews," interview by Mark A. Belnick [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1996 December 13 (Box 91)
    - Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison Litigation Luncheon honoring Liman [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1997 August 6 (Box 92)
    - "Arthur L. Liman Memorial" [original; sixty minutes; restricted]., 1997 September 22 (Box 93)
    - Liman Memorial tape [original; five minutes; restricted]., 1997 (Box 94)
    - Obituaries aired on various television programs [original; fifteen minutes; restricted]., 1997 (Box 95)
    - Arthur Liman Policy Institute of the Legal Action Center Benefit Reception [original; sixty minutes; restricted; Liman does not appear in this video]., 1998 November 17 (Box 96)
    - Commenting on the pardon of Casper Weinberger [original; fifteen minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 97)
    - Clips of news stories about the Iran-Contra hearings and the Milken trial [original; twenty minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 98)
    - Clips of news stories re: John Zaccaro pleading guilty, Liman giving statements to the press [original; thirty minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 99)
    - "CBS This Morning" interview re: Hillary Clinton subpoena to grand jury [original; ten minutes; restricted]., undated (Box 100)
  - U-matic videotape ["Judiciary and the Media," panel discussion about allowing television cameras in the courtroom (original; sixty minutes; restricted)]., 1978 December 11 (Box 101)
- Oversize
  - Attica State Prison uprising
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 102, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, [1971] (Box 102, Folder 2)